ABHINAV VERMA

http://averma.tech/

Computer Science \circ University of Texas at Austin

(217) 721-9461 \circ verma@utexas.edu

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research lies at the intersection of machine learning and formal methods. I am especially concerned with building trustworthy intelligent systems, using learning models that are provably safe, human interpretable, reliable, and robust to domain shifts.

EDUCATION

| University of Texas at Austin | August 2020 - Present |
|---|--|
| Ph.D. student o Computer Science Advisor: Prof. Swarat Chaudhuri | $Austin, \ TX$ |
| Rice University (Transferred to UT) Ph.D. student \circ Computer Science | $\begin{array}{c} August\ 2016\ \hbox{-}\ August\ 2020\\ Houston,\ TX \end{array}$ |
| University of Oregon M.S. • Mathematics | September 2012 - June 2014 Eugene, OR |
| Indian Institute of Science M.S. ∘ Mathematics | August 2008 - July 2011 Bangalore, India |
| University of Delhi - Hindu College B.A. Honors o Mathematics | July 2005 - June 2008 New Delhi, India |

PUBLICATIONS

Google Scholar Profile: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=jM1HeCIAAAAJ

Peer-Reviewed

1. Programmatically Interpretable Reinforcement Learning

<u>Abhinav Verma</u>, Vijayaraghavan Murali, Rishabh Singh, Pushmeet Kohli, Swarat Chaudhuri 35th International Conference on Machine Learning (**ICML**) 2018.

Acceptance Rate: 29.1%

Accepted as a Long Talk: Top 9% of submitted papers.

2. Representing Formal Languages: A Comparison of Finite Automata and Recurrent Neural Networks

Joshua J. Michalenko, Ameesh Shah, <u>Abhinav Verma</u>, Swarat Chaudhuri, Ankit B. Patel 7th International Conference on Learning Representations (**ICLR**) 2019.

Acceptance Rate: 31.4%

3. Control Regularization for Reduced Variance Reinforcement Learning Richard Cheng, <u>Abhinav Verma</u>, Gábor Orosz, Swarat Chaudhuri, Yisong Yue, Joel W. Burdick 36th International Conference on Machine Learning (**ICML**) 2019.

Acceptance Rate: 22.6%

- 4. Imitation-Projected Programmatic Reinforcement Learning <u>Abhinav Verma</u>, Hoang M. Le, Yisong Yue, Swarat Chaudhuri 33rd Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (**NeurIPS**) 2019. Acceptance Rate: 21.6%
- 5. Learning Differentiable Programs with Admissible Neural Heuristics Ameesh Shah, Eric Zhan, Jennifer J Sun, <u>Abhinav Verma</u>, Yisong Yue, Swarat Chaudhuri 34th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2020. Acceptance Rate: 20.1%
- 6. Neurosymbolic Reinforcement Learning with Formally Verified Exploration Greg Anderson, <u>Abhinav Verma</u>, Isil Dillig, Swarat Chaudhuri 34th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (**NeurIPS**) 2020. Acceptance Rate: 20.1%

Technical Report

Verifiable and Interpretable Reinforcement Learning through Program Synthesis
 <u>Abhinav Verma</u>
 Doctoral Consortium at The 33rd AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI) 2019.

Masters Thesis

 Irreducible Representations Of The Symmetric Group And The General Linear Group <u>Abhinav Verma</u>
 Department of Mathematics at The Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore 2011.

In Preparation

- Reachability Analysis and Constraints for Reinforcement Learning Abhinav Verma, Hoang M. Le, Susmit Jha, Yisong Yue, Swarat Chaudhuri.
- Neurosymbolic Policy Transfer for Autonomous Racing Cars <u>Abhinav Verma</u>, Surya S. Dwivedi, Joydeep Biswas, Swarat Chaudhuri.

AWARDS & HONORS

- Fellowship, J.P. Morgan AI Research PhD Fellowship 2020. \$100,000 award to support tuition, stipend, and travel.
- Research Award, Dean Award, School of Engineering, Rice University 2019.
- Bronze Medal, ACM Student Research Competition at Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI) 2018.
- Bronze Medal, ACM Student Research Competition at The 45th ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages (POPL) 2018.
- Fellowship, Council of Scientific & Industrial Research (NSF-Equivalent), India 2011.
- Scholarship, Ministry of Human Resource Development, India 2008-2010.

MENTORING

Six students co-advised, three from underrepresented groups, two associated publications.

Current

• Masters, Surya S Dwivedi, University of Texas at Austin. Project: Reinforcement learning for F1Tenth cars.

Abhinav Verma - CV 2 of 5

• Undergraduate, Myra Cheng, Caltech.

Project: Machine learning for behavioral neuroscience.

• Undergraduate, Joshua Deng, University of Texas at Austin.

Project: Learning programmatic models of RNA splicing.

Graduated

• Masters, Ameesh Shah, Rice University.

Project: Learning differentiable programs with admissible neural heuristics.

Currently: Graduate Student at UC Berkeley.

• Undergraduate, Jacqui Lee, Rice University.

Project: Adaptive therapies for Sepsis via reinforcement learning.

Currently: Graduate Student at MIT.

• Intern, Nirha Patel, University of California, San Diego.

Project: Evolutionary algorithms for reinforcement learning.

Currently: Developer at Yahoo.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Rice University

January 2017 - December 2019

Teaching Assistant

• COMP 539: Software Engineering Methodology.

Project based graduate course on software engineering.

• COMP 503: Reasoning About Software.

Graduate course on formal methods and automated reasoning.

 \bullet COMP 310: Advanced Object-Oriented Programming and Design.

Senior undergraduate course on OOP.

Wolfram Research

January 2015 - August 2016

Certified Instructor

- Conducted online corporate training for Mathematica users.
- Helped develop and improve courses based on newly introduced functionality.

University of Oregon

September 2012 - June 2014

Standalone Instructor

Approximately forty students in each class.

• Math 105: University Mathematics.

Introduction to logic, combinatorics, and probability.

Core requirement for BS degree.

• Math 111: College Algebra.

Foundational course in algebra, functions, and mathematical modeling.

Calculus preparation course, prerequisite for higher-level math courses.

• Math 112: Elementary Functions.

Focus on mathematical induction and trigonometric functions.

Precalculus designed for math, biology, physiology, and CS majors.

Abhinav Verma - CV 3 of 5

Teaching Assistant

• Math 243: Introduction to Probability and Statistics. Undergraduate course on statistical reasoning.

Dr. B. R. Ambedkar University

January 2012 - April 2012

Teaching Assistant

• M01: Introduction to Mathematical Thinking. First course on abstract mathematics.

INDUSTRIAL EXPERIENCE

SRI International

June 2019 - August 2019

Research Intern, Mentor: Susmit Jha

Menlo Park, CA

- Researched interpretable reinforcement learning via program synthesis.
- Integrated vision models with programmatic reinforcement learning.

Microsoft Research

June 2017 - September 2017

Research Intern, Mentor: Christoph M. Wintersteiger

Cambridge, UK

- Researched methods to use deep neural networks for quantifier instantiation in Z3.
- Intern in the Programming Principles and Tools group.

Wolfram Research

August 2014 - August 2016

Technology Engineer

Champaign, IL

- Researched integrating automated theorem proving into the Wolfram Language.
- Helped identify and implement new functionality based on cutting edge research.

AuntyCook

August 2011 - July 2012

New Delhi, India

 $Co ext{-}Founder$

- Conceptualized a business, creating a marketplace for the sale of home cooked meals.
- Used machine learning to optimize sales and deliveries.

SERVICE

Referee

- The 38th International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML) 2021.
- The 9th International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR) 2021.
- Machine Learning (Springer Journal).
- The 34th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2020.
- The 23rd International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS) 2020.
- The 32nd International Conference on Computer-Aided Verification (CAV) 2020.
- The 12th NASA Formal Methods Symposium (NFM) 2020.

Abhinav Verma - CV 4 of 5

Committees

University of Texas, Austin

• Junior Graduate Admissions Committee: responsible for initial screening of PhD applications.

Rice University

- Graduate Student Faculty Search Committee: responsible for feedback on faculty candidates.
- School of Engineering Co-op management committee.

Indian Institute of Science

- PC Member, Conference on Algebraic and Combinatorial Representation Theory.
- Student Committee, Indian Institute of Science Centenary Conference.

Delhi University

• Member Central Council: governing body of student union with fifty thousand members.

INVITED PARTICIPATION

- Institute for Foundations of Machine Learning Seminar, November 2020.
- Neurosymbolic Learning Seminar, University of Pennsylvania, October 2020.
- The New York Academy of Sciences, 14th Annual Machine Learning Symposium 2020.
- International Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems, Virtual 2020.
- International Conference on Computer-Aided Verification (CAV), New York 2019.
- International Conference on Machine Learning, Long Beach 2019.
- International Conference on Learning Representations, New Orleans 2019.
- International Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems, Vancouver 2019.
- Doctoroal Consortium at AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, Honolulu 2019.
- Deep Learning and Reinforcement Learning Summer School, University of Alberta 2019.
- Marktoberdorf Summer School on Engineering Secure and Dependable Software Systems 2018.
- International Conference on Machine Learning, Stockholm, Sweden 2018.
- Rice University Machine Learning Seminar, 2018.
- Wolfram Technology Conference, Champaign, Illinois 2014.
- Western Algebraic Geometry Symposium, University of Colorado, Boulder 2014.
- Graduate Student Topology and Geometry Conference, University of Texas, Austin 2014.
- Pacific Northwest Geometry Seminar, Stanford University 2014.
- Midwest Dynamical Systems Meeting, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign 2013.
- Workshop on Unitary Representations of Real Reductive Groups, University of Utah 2013.
- Graduate Student Topology and Geometry Conference, University of Notre Dame 2013.
- International Congress of Mathematicians (ICM), Hyderabad, India 2010.
- Conference on Algebraic and Combinatorial Approaches to Representation Theory, Bangalore, India 2010.
- Conference on Groups, Actions, Computations (GAC), Allahabad, India 2010.
- Conference on Analysis and its Applications, Bangalore, India 2009.
- Indian Institute of Science Centenary Conference, Bangalore, India, 2008.

Abhinav Verma - CV 5 of 5